C–H bonds are the most prevalent chemical bonds on the surface of organic and biomolecules. Better means for the selective and controllable functionalization of C–H bonds could greatly facilitate a broad range of applications such as tagging organic and biomolecules, drug development and mapping ligand–receptor interactions.1,2 Despite their tremendous potential, the low reactivity of C–H bonds and the difficulty of achieving selectivity pose a significant challenge for the realization of a C–H labeling strategy, especially for more inert aliphatic C–H bonds. Radical reactions could provide a simple yet powerful approach to selectively target specific aliphatic C–H bonds due to their inherent ability to differentiate aliphatic C–H bonds based on the bond dissociation energy.3–5 While various radical aliphatic C–H functionalization reactions have been well-studied, new methods with better reactivity, versatility and biocompatibility are necessary for the selective and efficient C–H labeling of complex substrates.
Among reported aliphatic C–H functionalization reactions, C–H azidation has proven to be particularly useful due to the unique photophysical and chemical reactivity of the azido group.6–14 In 1996, Zhdankin8 reported that the reaction of simple hydrocarbons with azidoiodane 1 in the presence of benzoyl peroxide led to the selective azidation of 3° and activated 2° C–H bonds in moderate to good yield.9–11 Hartwig recently discovered that Fe/PyBOX catalysts promote aliphatic C–H azidation with 1 under milder conditions, allowing the labeling of complex natural products with high selectivity.12,13 Herein, we report a new strategy to affect the azidation of 3° C–H bonds of complex substrates using the Zhdankin reagent 1, a photosensitizer and visible-light irradiation at room temperature (Scheme 1). Furthermore, this visible-light-promoted radical reaction system can be conveniently modulated by the addition of nucleophilic halides to achieve aliphatic C–H chlorination and bromination with high efficiency and chemospecificity.


image file: c5sc04169d-s1.tif
Scheme 1 A highly tunable radical-mediated reaction system for the selective functionalization of 3° C(sp3)–H bonds under the promotion of visible light.	
Results and discussion
Our research in radical C–H functionalization chemistry stems from our interest in the synthetic and biological studies of peptides.15 Compared with α-amino acid (αAA) residues bearing polar or aromatic side chains, the structural and functional roles of hydrophobic aliphatic αAA residues such as leucine and valine in peptides and proteins are much more difficult to probe due to the lack of suitable chemical handles in these residues. Following the report of Hartwig's Fe-catalyzed aliphatic C–H azidation,12 we wondered whether this azidation chemistry could potentially provide a long sought-after method for selectively labeling the aliphatic αAA residues of peptides and proteins. As shown in Table 1, we commenced our investigation with the azidation of N-phthaloyl leucine methyl ester 2 with 1 under various reported conditions (Table 1). The reaction of 2 under Fe/iPr-PyBOX-catalyzed conditions in CH3CN provided the desired azidated product 3 in low yield (entry 1). The reaction under benzoyl peroxide-promoted conditions also gave 3 in moderate yield (entry 4). Interestingly, the azidation of Leu 2 proceeded in good yield without any catalyst or additive at 80 °C in hexafluoroisopropanol (HFIP) under an air atmosphere, forming ortho-iodobenzoic acid as the main byproduct (entry 9).
Table 1 3° C–H azidation and chlorination of Leu 2
image file: c5sc04169d-u1.tif

Entry	Reagents (equiv.)/atmosphere	Solvent	T (°C)/time (h)	Yielda (%)
3	4
a Yields are based on 1H-NMR analysis on a 0.2 mmol scale. b VL: 12 W fluorescent bulb. c Isolated yield (see ESI).
1	Fe(OAc)2 (0.1), iPr-PyBOX (0.11), air	CH3CN	50/24	27	0
2	Fe(OAc)2 (0.1), air	CH3CN	50/24	30	0
3	Air	CH3CN	50/24	37	0
4	Benzoyl peroxide (0.2), air	DCE	50/24	41	0
5	Benzoyl peroxide (0.2), air	HFIP	rt/24	7	0
6	Air	CH3CN	80/24	42	0
7	Air	H2O	80/24	30	0
8	Air	DCM/H2O (1[thin space (1/6-em)]:[thin space (1/6-em)]9)	80/24	51	0
9	Air	HFIP	80/24	70	0
10	Ir(ppy)3 (0.05), WLb, Ar	HFIP	rt/24	<2	0
11	Ru(bpy)3Cl2 (0.05), VL, Ar	HFIP	rt/24	46	<5
12	Ru(bpy)3Cl2 (0.001), VL, Ar	HFIP	rt/24	91 (86c)	<3
13	Ru(bpy)3Cl2 (0.0001), VL, Ar	HFIP	rt/24	70	<3
14	Ru(bpy)3Cl2 (0.2), VL, Ar	HFIP	rt/24	15	35
15	Ru(bpy)3Cl2 (0.001), MgCl2 (2), VL, Ar	HFIP	rt/24	5	30
16	Ru(bpy)3Cl2 (0.001), TMSCl (2), VL, Ar	HFIP	rt/24	<2	87
17	Ru(bpy)Cl2 (0.001), LiCl (4), VL, Ar	HFIP	rt/24	<2	95 (77c)
18	LiCl (4), VL, Ar	HFIP	rt/24	0	0
19	Ru(bpy)3Cl2 (0.001), TEMPO (2), VL, Ar	HFIP	rt/24	<2	0
20	Ru(bpy)3Cl2 (0.001), Ar, in darkness	HFIP	rt/24	<2	0
21	VL, Ar (no Ru(bpy)3Cl2)	HFIP	rt/24	6	0

In order to achieve better biocompatibility, we next investigated whether the azidation reaction could proceed at room temperature. While the use of various electron transfer reagents such as zinc metal and cerium ammonium nitrate failed, we were delighted to find that the application of a photosensitizer (Ru(bpy)3Cl2) and visible light irradiation (VL: 12 W household fluorescent light bulb) formed 3 in moderate yield under an Ar atmosphere (entry 11).16 Interestingly, the use of 0.1 mol% of Ru(bpy)3Cl2 gave significantly improved results than when using 5 mol% of Ru(bpy)3Cl2 (entry 12). Furthermore, we were surprised to find that the use of 20 mol% of Ru(bpy)3Cl2 produced only a small amount of 3 but instead produced a 35% yield of chlorinated product 4 (entry 14). This result prompted us to evaluate different Cl donors to improve the yield of the chlorinated product (see ESI† for more screening results). A number of nucleophilic Cl sources worked, LiCl or TMSCl gave 4 in the highest yield and selectivity (entries 16 and 17). The addition of 2 equiv. of TEMPO shut down the reaction with little conversion of 2 (entry 19). The reaction in darkness gave little product (entry 20). Interestingly, visible light irradiation in the absence of Ru(bpy)3Cl2 also gave a small amount of 3 (entry 21).

As shown in Scheme 2, C–H azidation reactions with azidoiodane 1 worked well for a variety of aliphatic substrates with excellent 3° C–H selectivity under the optimized light-promoted conditions A.17 Common functional groups e.g. Boc, Bn, TBS, ester and amide were well tolerated. Steric hindrance and electron-withdrawing functional groups generally diminish the reactivity of the neighbouring C–H bonds, allowing preferential labeling of certain 3° C–H bonds of complex substrates.1b,e For instance, azidation selectively took place at the more distal 3° carbon of 13 and N-phthaloyl pregabalin methyl ester 15. Moreover, we were delighted to find that the C–H azidation of dipeptides under the standard light-promoted conditions also provided good yield and excellent selectivity (see 17 and 18).


image file: c5sc04169d-s2.tif
Scheme 2 Substrate scope of aliphatic C–H azidation. [a] Isolated yield on a 0.2 mmol scale. [b] 1H-NMR yield. Isolated yield was occasionally compromised by the volatility of the product and/or difficulties in purification. [c] Isolated yield of its amide derivative (see ESI†). [d] As the only major product.	
As shown in Scheme 3, visible light-promoted 3° C–H chlorination reactions with azidoiodane 1 and LiCl as the Cl donor also demonstrated excellent efficiency, site-selectivity and functional group tolerance.18 The reactivity of these C–H chlorination reactions was slightly higher than the corresponding azidation reaction (see 21vs.10 and 24vs.18). Additionally, we were pleased to find that this reaction system can be further modulated to form 3° C–H brominated products by the addition of a bromide donor.19,20 As shown in Scheme 4, the reaction of various aliphatic substrates with 2 equiv. of nBu4NBr, 2 equiv. of 1, and 2 mol% of Ru(bpy)3Cl2 under visible light irradiation (conditions C) gave 3° C–H brominated products in good yield and with excellent selectivity. It is worth noting that the competing C–H azidation process was completely suppressed in both chlorination and bromination reaction systems.


image file: c5sc04169d-s3.tif
Scheme 3 Substrate scope of C–H chlorination. (a) Isolated yield on a 0.2 mmol scale and (b) 1H-NMR yield.	

image file: c5sc04169d-s4.tif
Scheme 4 Substrate scope of C–H bromination. (a) Isolated yield on a 0.2 mmol scale; (b) added in 2 portions (1 + 1 equiv.).	
The azidation reactions under the newly developed conditions are consistent with the radical chain mechanisms proposed by Zhdankin8 (Scheme 5A). The radical chain mechanism is supported by the large quantum yield (Φ ∼ 18, measured by Yoon's method21) of the C–H azidation reaction of 32 with 1 (see ESI†). Under thermally promoted conditions (see entry 9, Table 1), the weak I–N3 bond of 1 presumably undergoes homolytic cleavage to form an iodanyl radical I and an azido radical.8 Because of the relative weak reactivity the of N3 radical,22I likely serves as the H abstractor23 to convert the C–H substrate to a C-centered radical intermediate II. II then attacks 1 to form the azidated product and regenerates I, which propagates the radical chain reaction. Under visible-light irradiation in the presence of Ru(bpy)3Cl2, 1 may be activated by electron transfer24 to generate radical I, which can trigger the same chain reaction at rt. The chlorination reactions likely share the same mechanism for the azidoiodane-mediated radical initiation step (formation of I) as the azidation reactions. However, chloroiodane 31[thin space (1/6-em)]25 formed via in situ substitution of 1 with Cl− probably overrides azidoiodane in the subsequent chain propagation step to selectively form the C–H chlorinated products (Scheme 5B). Our control experiments indicated that both 1 and 31 are involved in the chlorination reaction. As shown in eqn 4, mixing of 1 and LiCl in HFIP at rt in the absence of light can form 31 (42% yield in 12 h). Subjecting substrate 32 and 2 equiv. of pre-made 31 to the standard light-promoted conditions did not give any reaction (eqn 5). Interestingly, the addition of 1 equiv. of 1 together with 31 cleanly restored the chlorination reaction (see more details in ESI†).26 This suggests that chloride 31 cannot be directly activated to generate the iodanyl radical I for the initial H-abstraction, but is more reactive than azidoiodane toward nucleophilic attack by the radical intermediate II. C–H bromination with nBu4NBr may follow a similar pathway as chlorination.


image file: c5sc04169d-s5.tif
Scheme 5 Plausible mechanisms for C–H azidation and chlorination.	
Conclusions
In summary, we have developed a uniquely tunable radical-mediated reaction system for the azidation and halogenation of tertiary aliphatic C–H bonds of various substrates with azidoiodane 1 and visible light irradiation at room temperature. These reactions provide a simple and powerful method for selectively labeling tertiary aliphatic C–H bonds of organic molecules with diverse tags. In addition to a mild protocol for radical aliphatic C–H functionalization, this study demonstrated a novel strategy to use more easily available nucleophilic halide reagents for radical C–H halogenation reactions. Further mechanistic studies and expansion of this reaction system to achieve other types of aliphatic C–H functionalization and applications in labeling biomolecules are currently under investigation.
Acknowledgements
We gratefully thank the State Key Laboratory of Elemento-Organic Chemistry at Nankai University for financial support of this work. 
A dual photoredox and gold-catalysed cross-coupling reaction of alkynyltrimethylsilanes and aryldiazonium tetrafluoroborates is described. The reaction proceeds through visible-light mediated oxidative addition of aryldiazoniums, transmetalation of alkynyltrimethylsilanes and aryl–alkynyl reductive elimination. Exclusive selectivity for silyl-substituted alkynes is observed, with no reactivity observed for terminal alkynes.

Graphical abstract: Visible light-mediated gold-catalysed carbon(sp2)–carbon(sp) cross-coupling
This article is part of the themed collections: ISACS19: Challenges in Organic Chemistry and Top 50 Articles of 2016: Organic Chemistry
Introduction
For over a decade, homogeneous gold catalysis has been investigated because it provides access to novel modes of reactivity and enables rapid generation of complex molecular architectures.1 However, in contrast to other low-valent late transition metal catalysts, the majority of gold(i) complexes are unreactive towards the oxidative addition of aryl and vinyl halides and pseudohalides.2 Consequently, most gold-catalysed cross-coupling reactions have required sacrificial oxidants to access the +3 oxidation state.3 For example, this reactivity platform has been exploited in a gold-catalysed oxidative coupling of organosilanes and 1,2-alkene functionalizations (Scheme 1A). As an alternative, visible light-mediated oxidative addition of aryldiazoniums has emerged as a method for the generation of the requisite gold(iii) intermediates via photoredox catalysis, thereby obviating the need for sacrificial oxidants.4 These gold(iii) intermediates have been intercepted by a variety of nucleophiles in dual catalytic photoredox–gold reactions (Scheme 1B).

 
Scheme 1  Photoredox catalyst and visible light-mediated AuI/AuIII catalysis.
Although aryldiazoniums and photoredox catalysts provide an efficient method to generate gold(iii) intermediates, several challenges must be addressed in order to facilitate carbon–carbon cross-coupling via these species. First, aryldiazonium salts are highly electrophilic and reactive towards many classes of nucleophilic coupling partners. Aryldiazoniums are generally decomposed under Kumada and Negishi coupling conditions and do not tolerate ligand additives and stoichiometric bases employed in the majority of Suzuki, Sonogashira and Hiyama coupling reactions.5 Second, as visible light-mediated oxidative addition of aryldiazoniums is proposed to proceed through radical intermediates, nucleophilic coupling partners that can participate in single electron transfer, such as organotin and organotrifluoroborates compounds, are problematic.6 Inspired by the oxidative coupling of organosilanes, we envisioned that the gold(iii) complexes generated via photoredox catalysis might undergo transmetalation with organosilanes, generating an intermediate poised for carbon–carbon bond formation through reductive elimination.7,8

Results and discussions
While aryldiazonium tetrafluoroborates have been shown to react with halo-, azido-, allyl- and thiotrimethylsilanes, their reactions with alkynyltrimethylsilanes has not been previously reported.9 Additionally, previous reports of organosilane transmetallation with gold lead us to hypothesize that the transmetallation of alkynyltrimethylsilanes to gold(iii) intermediates might result in productive cross-coupling. On the basis of this hypothesis, we examined the combined gold/photoredox coupling of 1 equivalent of aryldiazonium salt 1a and 1 equivalent of alkynyltrimethylsilane 2.

Evaluation of reaction conditions showed that the combination of Ar3PAuCl and Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2, in acetonitrile gave the highest yield of aryl alkyne 3a (Table 1). Changing either the solvent or the photoredox catalyst proved detrimental to the yield of the desired product. With respect to the ligands on the gold catalyst, both electronic and steric factors impacted the efficiency of the cross-coupling. For example, electron-deficient triarylphosphine ligands resulted in significantly lower yield of 3a (Table 1, entry 10). The sterics of the ligand showed an even more dramatic effect on reaction yield. The reaction conducted with (p-tol)3PAuCl provided 72% yield of the desired product, while the much more hindered (o-tol)3PAuCl-catalysed reaction only provided 17% yield of 3a (Table 1, entry 11 and 12). The yield of product was lower when tricyclohexylphosphinegold(i) chloride was used as catalyst instead of triphenylphoshinegold(i) chloride (Table 1, entry 13). Gold(i) complexes of dialkylbiarylphosphine were also examined, but all showed less than 5% yield due to the combined effect of dialkyl groups and the steric effect of biaryl groups. Finally, no coupling product was observed in the absence of the ruthenium catalyst (entry 14) or when the reaction was conducted in the dark (entry 15).

Table 1 Optimization of reaction conditions
 image file: c5sc03025k-u1.tif
Entry	Gold cat.	Photoredox cat.	Solvent	Yielda
1	Ph3PAuCl	Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2	CH3CN	70
2	Ph3PAuCl	Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2	Acetone	39
3	Ph3PAuCl	Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2	CH3NO2	15
4	Ph3PAuCl	Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2	DMF	10
5	Ph3PAuCl	Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2	MeOH	18
6	Ph3PAuCl	Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2	EtOH	4
7	Ph3PAuCl	Ir(ppy)3	CH3CN	21
8	Ph3PAuCl	Ir(ppy)2(dtbbpy)PF6	CH3CN	45
9	(p-MeOPh)3PAuCl	Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2	CH3CN	73
10	(p-CF3Ph)3PAuCl	Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2	CH3CN	43
11	(p-tol)3PAuCl	Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2	CH3CN	72
12	(o-tol)3PAuCl	Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2	CH3CN	17
13	Cy3PAuCl	Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2	CH3CN	48
14	Ph3PAuCl	—	CH3CN	0
15b	Ph3PAuCl	Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2	CH3CN	0
Reaction conditions: 4-fluorobenzenediazonium tetrafluoroborate 1a (0.2 mmol, 1 equiv.), 1-trimethylsilyl-2-phenylacetylene 2 (0.2 mmol, 1 equiv.), gold catalyst (5 mol%), photoredox catalyst (1 mol%), solvent (2 mL), N2 atmosphere, visible light, rt for 6 h. a GC yields. b The reaction was run in the dark. bpy = 2,2′-bipyridine, ppy = 2-phenylpyridine, dtbbpy = 4,4′-di-tert-butyl-2,2′-bipyridine.
With an optimized catalyst system in hand, the scope with respect to the aryldiazonium coupling partner was examined (Table 2). The yields of alkynylation reactions of electron-poor aryldiazonium salts were generally higher than those of reactions with electron-rich aryldiazonium coupling partners. It should be noted that the intrinsic instability of ortho-substituted aryldiazonium salts limited their use in this transformation (Table 2, entry 3k and 3l). It is also noteworthy that all halogen substitutions on the aryldiazonium coupling partner were preserved during the coupling reaction. Bromo- and iodoaryldiazonium salts were readily coupled and leaving halides intact for use in further reactions (Table 2, 3b and 3j); this chemoselectivity is challenging under typical palladium-catalysed Sonogashira coupling reactions.10

Table 2 Scope of aryldiazonium tetrafluoroborates
 image file: c5sc03025k-u2.tif
Reaction conditions: 1a–l (0.24 mmol, 1.2 equiv.), 2 (0.2 mmol, 1.0 equiv.), Ph3PAuCl (10 mol%), Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2 (2 mol%), acetonitrile (2 mL), N2 atmosphere, visible light, rt for 3 h. Isolated yields.
The difference in reactivity of electron-rich and -poor aryldiazoniums may be the result of competing reaction pathways. Oxidative addition is believed to proceed through single electron reduction of aryldiazoniums and this process is preferred with electron-poor aryldiazonium salts.4 On the other hand, the generation of aryl cations, through loss of dinitrogen, is facile with electron-rich aryldiazoniums. Correspondingly, we observed trace amount of desired product when benzenediazonium tetrafluoroborate was heated at 60 °C for 9 hours in the presence of 1-trimethylsilyl-2-(4-methoxy)phenylacetylene; however the same reactivity was not observed with 4-fluorophenyldiazonium salts on the same conditions.

The scope of alkynyltrimethylsilanes was also investigated (Table 3). Both aryl- and alkylethynyltrimethylsilanes were coupled with modest to high product yields. o-Isopropylphenyl, biphenylyl and naphthylalkynyltrimethylsilanes participated in the gold-catalysed coupling (Table 3, 3m, 3n and 3o). Potentially sensitive benzylic and propargylic C–H and C–X bonds were well tolerated under the reaction conditions (Table 3, 3q, 3aa and 3s–v). Additionally, alkynyltrimethylsilane 3w was prepared in 78% yield from the coupling of aryldiazonium salt 1d and bis(trimethylsilyl)acetylene, providing a compliment to using trimethylsilylacetylene in a traditional Sonogashira coupling (Table 3, 3w).

Table 3 Scope of alkynyltrimethylsilanes
 image file: c5sc03025k-u3.tif
Reaction conditions: 1d (0.24 mmol, 1.2 equiv.), 2m–aa (0.2 mmol, 1.0 equiv.), Ph3PAuCl (10 mol%), Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2 (2 mol%), acetonitrile (2 mL), N2 atmosphere, visible light, rt for 3 h. Isolated yields. Ar = p-nitrophenyl. a 5 equiv. of bis(trimethylsilyl)acetylene was used with 1 equiv. of 1d. b GC yields.
Another interesting feature of this reaction is the effect of the silyl group on yield (Table 4). When trimethylsilylacetylene was coupled with 1d to generate terminal alkyne 3x, the yield was 15% with none of the corresponding silylacetylene 3w (Table 3). This observation suggests that, under the current base free reaction conditions, the silyl group plays a critical role in the coupling. To investigate this role, a set of reactions was performed by varying counteranions of aryldiazonium salts and silyl group identities of alkynylsilanes. The yield of coupling product was diminished as the steric hindrance of silyl group was increased (Table 4, entry 1 and entries 4–7). While both tetrafluoroborate and tosylate diazonium salts proved efficient coupling partners, the yield was diminished when hexafluorophosphate salts were used.11 Moreover, when the corresponding terminal alkyne was used instead of alkynyltrimethylsilanes, only 3% of the coupling product was observed (Table 4, entry 8).12 Taken together, these results suggests that transmetallation from the organosilane is critical for high efficiency of the current coupling reaction.

Table 4 Effect of counteranion and silyl group
 image file: c5sc03025k-u4.tif
Entry	Counteranion (X)	Silyl group (Y)	Yielda
1	BF4−	TMS	70
2	TsO−	TMS	68
3	PF6−	TMS	24
4	BF4−	TES	61
5	BF4−	TBDMS	10
6	BF4−	TIPS	10
7	BF4−	TBDPS	1
8	BF4−	H	3
Reaction conditions: aryldiazonium salt (0.2 mmol, 1 equiv.), phenylethynylsilane (0.2 mmol, 1 equiv.), Ph3PAuCl (5 mol%), Ru(bpy)3(PF6)2 (1 mol%), acetonitrile (2 mL), N2 atmosphere, visible light, rt for 6 h. a GC yields.
Other organotrimethylsilanes were tested under the optimized reaction conditions. While the reactions of aryl and vinylsilanes were complicated by competing reactions,13,14 the gold/photoredox-catalysed coupling of allenyltrimethylsilane 4 provided propargylic compound 5 as the sole coupling product (Scheme 2). The product from aryl–allenyl reductive elimination and the other aryl–propargylic coupling isomer were prepared independently (Scheme 2, 6 and 7). We examined whether 6 was an intermediate that underwent isomerization to 5 facilitated by visible light and the photoredox catalyst. However, no isomerization was observed of 6 to either 5 or 7 under the reaction conditions. Therefore, the formation of 5 is best rationalized by transmetalation of 4 to the gold(iii) intermediate, followed by 1,3-migration and aryl–propargyl reductive elimination.

 
Scheme 2  Reaction with allenyltrimethylsilanes.
Conclusions
In summary, we have demonstrated that trimethylsilylalkynes and aryldiazonium tetrafluoroborates can be coupled via dual photoredox and gold catalysis strategy. The reaction proceeds under mild conditions and shows excellent functional group tolerance, including aryl halides that may be reactive under traditional coupling conditions. This process compliments the Sonogashira coupling, especially when aryl–alkynyl coupling is required under non-basic conditions and may present an advantage when TMS-alkynes are available rather than corresponding terminal alkynes.