Chapter 9
The Normal Curve

The normal curve is one of a number of possible models of probability distributions. Because it is widely used and is an important theoretical tool, it merits its own chapter in this book.

The normal curve is not a single curve, rather it is an infinite number of possible curves, all described by the same algebraic expression:

The Algebraic Expression that Describes the Normal Curve

Upon viewing this expression for the first time the initial reaction of the student is usually to panic. Don't. In general it is not necessary to "know" this formula to appreciate and use the normal curve. It is, however, useful to examine this expression for an understanding of how the normal curve operates.

First, some symbols in the expression are simply numbers. These symbols include "2", "p", and "e". The latter two are irrational numbers that are very long, p equaling 3.1416... and e equaling 2.81.... As discussed in the chapter on the review of algebra, it is possible to raise a "funny number", in this case "e", to a "funny power".

The second set of symbols that are of some interest includes the symbol "X", which is a variable corresponding to the score value. The height of the curve at any point is a function of X.

Thirdly, the final two symbols in the equation, "m " and "d " are called parameters, or values that, when set to particular numbers, define one of the infinite number of possible normal curves with which one is dealing. The concept of parameters is very important and considerable attention will be given them in the rest of this chapter. The Greek symbols "m " and "d " are often written in English as mu and sigma, respectively.

               
A Family of Distributions
The normal curve is called a family of distributions. Each member of the family is determined by setting the parameters (m and d ) of the model to a particular value (number). Because the m parameter can take on any value, positive or negative, and the d parameter can take on any positive value, the family of normal curves is quite large, consisting of an infinite number of members. This makes the normal curve a general-purpose model, able to describe a large number of naturally occurring phenomena, from test scores to the size of the stars.

Similarity of Members of the Family of Normal Curves
All the members of the family of normal curves, although different, have a number of properties in common. These properties include: shape, symmetry, tails approaching but never touching the X-axis, and area under the curve.

Bell shape - All members of the family of normal curves share the same bell shape, given the X-axis is scaled properly. Most of the area under the curve falls in the middle. The tails of the distribution (ends) approach the X-axis but never touch, with very little of the area under them.




Bilateral symmetry - All members of the family of normal curves are bilaterally symmetric. That is, if any normal curve was drawn on a two-dimensional surface (a piece of paper), cut out, and folded through the third dimension, the two sides would be exactly alike. Human beings are approximately bilaterally symmetrical, with a right and left side.




Tails never touch x-axis - All members of the family of normal curves have tails that approach, but never touch, the X-axis. The implication of this property is that no matter how far one travels along the number line, in either the positive or negative direction, there will still be some area under any normal curve. Thus, in order to draw the entire normal curve one must have an infinitely long line. Because most of the area under any normal curve falls within a limited range of the number line, only that part of the line segment is drawn for a particular normal curve.




Area under curve totals 1.00 - All members of the family of normal curves have a total area of one (1.00) under the curve, as do all probability models or models of frequency distributions. This property, in addition to the property of symmetry, implies that the area in each half of the distribution is .50 or one half.


           
In statistics, the area under a curve represents theoretical relative frequency or probability. It permits the statistician to make decisions about the world based on a belief about what the world looks like rather than the limited information available in a sample of scores. For example, the statistician would advise the shoe store owner to purchase shoes to stock his or her shelves based on the area under a normal curve model of the world rather than the proportion of individuals in the sample who wore a particular size shoe. Area under a curve may seem like a strange notion to many introductory statistics students, so let's take a brief look at it.

Area is a familiar concept. For example, the area of a square is s2, or side squared; the area of a rectangle is length times height; the area of a right triangle is one-half base times height; and the area of a circle is pr2 or p * r2. It is valuable to know these formulas if one is purchasing such things as carpeting, shingles, etc.

Areas may be added or subtracted from one another to find some resultant area. For example, suppose one had an L-shaped room and wished to purchase new carpet. One could find the area by taking the total area of the larger rectangle and subtracting the area of the rectangle that was not needed, or one could divide the area into two rectangles, find the area of each, and add the areas together. Both procedures are illustrated below:

Area in Rectangles

Finding the area under a curve poses a slightly different problem. In some cases there are formulas that directly give the area between any two points; finding these formulas are what integral calculus is all about. In other cases the areas must be approximated. Whether using integral calculus or approximating methods, the mathematician relies on the idea of adding together the areas of a number of rectangles.

Suppose a curve was divided into equally spaced intervals on the X-axis and a rectangle drawn corresponding to the height of the curve at any of the intervals. The rectangles may be drawn either smaller that the curve, or larger, as in the two illustrations below:

Approximating Area under Curves

Approximating the Area under a Curve

In either case, if the areas of all the rectangles under the curve were added together, the sum of the areas would be an approximation of the total area under the curve. In the case of the smaller rectangles, the area would be too small; in the case of the latter, they would be too big. Taking the average would give a better approximation, but mathematical methods provide a better way.

A better approximation may be achieved by making the intervals on the X-axis smaller. Such an approximations is illustrated below, more closely approximating the actual area under the curve.

A Better Approximation using Smaller Intervals

The actual area of the curve may be calculated by making the intervals infinitely small (no distance between the intervals) and then computing the area. If this last statement seems a bit bewildering, you share the bewilderment with millions of introductory calculus students. At this point the introductory statistics student must say "I believe" and trust the mathematician or enroll in an introductory calculus course.

           
Drawing a Member of the Family of Normal Curves
The standard procedure for drawing a normal curve is to draw a bell-shaped curve and an X-axis. A tick is placed on the X-axis corresponding to the highest point (middle) of the curve. Three ticks are then placed to both the right and left of the middle point. These ticks are equally spaced and include all but a very small portion under the curve. The middle tick is labeled with the value of mu (m) ; sequential ticks to the right are labeled by adding the value of sigma (d). Ticks to the left are labeled by subtracting the value of d from m for the three values. For example, if m =52 and d =12, then the middle value would be labeled with 52, points to the right would have the values of 64 (52 + 12), 76, and 88, and points to the left would have the values 40, 28, and 16. An example is presented below:

A Normal Curve with mu=52 and sigma=12

                   
Differences in Members of the Family of Normal Curves
Differences in members of the family of normal curves are a direct result of differences in values for parameters. The two parameters, m and d, each change the shape of the distribution in a different manner.

The first, m, determines where the midpoint of the distribution falls. Changes in m, without changes in d, result in moving the distribution to the right or left, depending upon whether the new value of m was larger or smaller than the previous value, but does not change the shape of the distribution. An example of how changes in m affect the normal curve are presented below:

Comparing Normal Curves with Different Values of Mu

Changes in the value of d , on the other hand, change the shape of the distribution without affecting the midpoint, because d affects the spread or the dispersion of scores. The larger the value of d, the more dispersed the scores; the smaller the value, the less dispersed. Perhaps the easiest way to understand how d affects the distribution is graphically. The distribution below demonstrates the effect of increasing the value of d :

A Normal Curve with Mu=52 and Sigma=24

Since this distribution was drawn according to the procedure described earlier, it appears similar to the previous normal curve, except for the values on the X-axis. This procedure effectively changes the scale and hides the real effect of changes in d . Suppose the second distribution was drawn on a rubber sheet instead of a sheet of paper and stretched to twice its original length in order to make the two scales similar. Drawing the two distributions on the same scale results in the following graphic:

Comparing Normal Curves with Different Values of Sigma

Note that the shape of the second distribution has changed dramatically, being much flatter than the original distribution. It must not be as high as the original distribution because the total area under the curve must be constant, that is, 1.00. The second curve is still a normal curve; it is simply drawn on a different scale on the X-axis.

A different effect on the distribution may be observed if the size of d is decreased. Below the new distribution is drawn according to the standard procedure for drawing normal curves:

A Normal Curve with Mu=52 and Sigma=6

Now both distributions are drawn on the same scale, as outlined immediately above, except in this case the sheet is stretched before the distribution is drawn and then released in order that the two distributions are drawn on similar scales:

Comparing Normal Curves with Different Values of Sigma

Note that the distribution is much higher in order to maintain the constant area of 1.00, and the scores are much more closely clustered around the value of m, or the midpoint, than before.

An interactive exercise is provided to demonstrate how the normal curve changes as a function of changes in m and d. The exercise starts by presenting a curve with m = 70 and d = 10. The student may change the value of m from 50 to 90 by moving the scroll bar on the bottom of the graph. In a similar manner, the value of d can be adjusted from 5 to 15 by changing the scroll bar on the right side of the graph.

   
Finding Area Under Normal Curves
Suppose that when ordering shoes to restock the shelves in the store one knew that female shoe sizes were normally distributed with m = 7.0 and d = 1.1. Don't worry about where these values came from at this point, there will be plenty about that later. If the area under this distribution between 7.75 and 8.25 could be found, then one would know the proportion of size eight shoes to order. The values of 7.75 and 8.25 are the real limits of the interval of size eight shoes.

The Area under a Normal Curve

Finding scores and areas on normal curves is easy using the probability calculator; simply select the normal distribution, enter values into the correct boxes, and click on a button. The area or score will be entered in the correct box and a representation of the curve will be drawn in the display area. The initial screen of the probability calculator appears below.

 The initial screen of the probability calculator.

Area below a Score
To find the area below 7.75 on a normal curve with mu =7.0 and sigma=1.1 complete the following steps.

Click on the selection "Area Below" under the "Normal Distribution"


Click on the "Normal Distribution" button.


Enter mu, sigma and the score in the labeled boxes.


Click on the button with the arrow pointing to the right.


The steps and the result are presented in the figure below.
Probability Calculator

Area between Scores
To find the area between scores, use the probability calculator and the steps outlined below.

1. Click on the selection "Area Between" under the "Normal Distribution"

2. Click on the "Normal Distribution" button.

3. Enter mu, sigma, low score, and high score in the labeled boxes.

4. Click on the button with the arrow pointing to the right.

The steps and the result are presented in the figure below.

Finding the Area under a Normal Curve Between Scores 

Area Above a Score
To find the area above a score, use the probability calculator and the steps outlined below.

1. Click on the selection "Area Above" under the "Normal Distribution"

2. Click on the "Normal Distribution" button.

3. Enter mu, sigma, and value in the labeled boxes.

4. Click on the button with the arrow pointing to the right.

The steps and the result is presented in the figure below.

Finding Area above a Score

Finding Probabilities in Both Tails
At times it will be necessary to find the area that falls in both the tail beyond a single score and the area in the tail of the mirror image of the score. For example in a normal distribution with mu equal 100, sigma equal 3, and a score of 105.3, one might wish to find the total area to the right of a value of 105.3 and to the left of 94.7. The value of 94.7 is the same distance from mu as the score of 105.3, as 105.3 - 100 = 5.3 and 94.7 - 100 = -5.3. This area can be found on the probability calculator using the following three steps.

1. Click on the selection "Two-tailed Sig. level" under the "Normal Distribution"

2. Click on the "Normal Distribution" button.

3. Enter mu, sigma, and value in the labeled boxes.

4. Click on the button with the arrow pointing to the right.

The steps and the result are presented in the figure below.

 Finding two-tailed significance level under a normal curve 

If a value of 94.7 had been entered as the value in the above illustration of the probability calculator, the same result would have occurred.

Probability Calculator
Finding Scores from Area
In some applications of the normal curve, it will be necessary to find the scores that cut off some proportion or percentage of area of the normal distribution. One such application is finding two scores that cut off some symmetrical middle area of a given normal curve. The scores form a confidence interval around the middle point set by the value of mu. Confidence intervals are used to give a range of values rather than a single value to a given measure or estimate. Confidence intervals incorporate error or uncertainty into the information that is given to the client or reader. For example, if finding a ninety-five percent (.95 area) confidence interval resulted in a low score of 83.72 and a high score of 95.87, then ninety-five times out of one hundred the true score will fall between those two points.

Other applications, namely that of finding the percentile rank based on the normal curve, require the ability to find the score value that cuts off a given area of a normal curve. For example, a score value that cuts off 20 percent (.20 area) of a given normal curve would be said to have a percentile rank of 20. The probability calculator has the ability to find both types of scores given area.

It is important to note, however, that interpretation of scores obtained from the normal in this manner are dependent upon the assumptions underlying the their construction to be reasonable. In order for a percentile rank based on the normal curve to be a valid estimate, the underlying distribution must be a normal distribution with the correct parameters of mu and sigma.

Finding Scores that Cut Off Middle Area
To find the scores that cut off some proportion or percentage of area of the normal distribution, it will be necessary to enter mu, sigma, and a probability value into the Probability Calculator. For example, suppose one wished to know what two scores cut off the middle 75% of a normal distribution with m = 123 and d = 23. The score values are used to find confidence intervals for various scores and statistics. In order to answer questions of this nature, the following steps can be used in the probability calculator.

1. Click on the selection "Confidence Interval" under the "Normal Distribution"

2. Click on the "Normal Distribution" button.

3. Enter mu, sigma, and Probability in the labeled boxes.

4. Click on the button with the arrow pointing to the left.

The steps and the result are presented in the figure below.

Finding Scores on a Normal Curve Given Area

Finding Scores that Cut off Bottom Area
In a similar manner, the score value which cuts of the bottom proportion of a given normal curve can be found using the program. For example a score of 138.52 cuts off .75 of a normal curve with mu=123 and sigma=23. This area was found using Normal Curve Area program in the following manner.

1. Click on the words "Area Below" under the "Normal Distribution"

2. Click on the "Normal Distribution" button.

3. Enter mu, sigma, and Probability in the labeled boxes.

4. Click on the button with the arrow pointing to the left.

Area Below a Given Score on a Normal Curve

In this case, a score of 138.5 would have a percentile rank of seventy-five in a normal distribution with mu equal 123 and sigma equal 23.


The Standard Normal Curve
The standard normal curve is a member of the family of normal curves with m = 0.0 and d = 1.0. The value of 0.0 was selected because the normal curve is symmetrical around m and the number system is symmetrical around 0.0. The value of 1.0 for d is simply a unit value. The X-axis on a standard normal curve is often relabeled and called z-scores.

There are three areas on a standard normal curve that all introductory statistics students should know. The first is that the total area below (to the left of) 0.0 is .50, as the standard normal curve is symmetrical like all normal curves. This result generalizes to all normal curves in that the total area below the value of mu is .50 on any member of the family of normal curves.

Area Below 0 on a Standard Normal Curve

The second area that should be memorized is between z-scores of -1.00 and +1.00. It is .68 or 68%.

Area Between Plus and Minus One Sigma Unit

The total area between plus and minus one sigma unit on any member of the family of normal curves is also .68.

The third area is between z-scores of -2.00 and +2.00 and is .95 or 95%.

Area Between Plus and Minus Two Sigma Units

This area (.95) also generalizes to plus and minus two sigma units on any normal curve.

Knowing these areas allow computation of additional areas. For example, the area between a z-score of 0.0 and 1.0 may be found by taking 1/2 the area between z-scores of -1.0 and 1.0, because the distribution is symmetrical between those two points. The answer in this case is .34 or 34%. A similar logic and answer is found for the area between 0.0 and -1.0 because the standard normal distribution is symmetrical around the value of 0.0.

The area below a z-score of 1.0 may be computed by adding .34 and .50 to get .84. The area above a z-score of 1.0 may now be computed by subtracting the area just obtained from the total area under the distribution (1.00), giving a result of 1.00 - .84 or .16 or 16%.

The area between -2.0 and -1.0 requires additional computation. First, the area between 0.0 and -2.0 is 1/2 of .95 or .475. Because the .475 includes too much area, the area between 0.0 and -1.0 (.34) must be subtracted in order to obtain the desired result. The correct answer is .475 - .34 or .135.

Area Under a Standard Normal Curve

Using a similar kind of logic to find the area between z-scores of .5 and 1.0 will result in an incorrect answer because the curve is not symmetrical around .5. The correct answer must be something less than .17, because the desired area is on the smaller side of the total divided area. Because of this difficulty, the areas can be found using the probability calculator. Entering the following information will produce the correct answer

Finding the Area Under a Standard Normal Curve

The following formula is used to transform a given normal distribution into the standard normal distribution. It was much more useful when area between and below a score was only contained in tables of the standard normal distribution. It is included here for both historical reasons and because it will appear in a different form later in this text.

Converting a Given Normal Curve to a Standard Normal Curve



       
Summary
The normal curve is an infinite number of possible probability models called a family of distributions. Each member of the family is described by setting the parameters (m and d) of the distribution to particular values. The members of the family are similar in that they share the same shape, are symmetrical, and have a total area underneath of 1.00. They differ in where the midpoint of the distribution falls, determined by m , and in the variability of scores around the midpoint, determined by d. The area between any two scores and the scores which cut off a given area on any given normal distribution can be easily found using the Probability Calculator provided with this text

Chapter 4
Module Fundamentals
4.1 Modules and Algebras
4.1.1 Definitions and Comments
A vector space M over a field R is a set of objects called vectors, which can be added,
subtracted and multiplied by scalars (members of the underlying field). Thus M is an
abelian group under addition, and for each r ∈ R and x ∈ M we have an element rx ∈ M.
Scalar multiplication is distributive and associative, and the multiplicative identity of the
field acts as an identity on vectors. Formally,
r(x + y) = rx + ry; (r + s)x = rx + sx; r(sx)=(rs)x; 1x = x
for all x, y ∈ M and r, s ∈ R. A module is just a vector space over a ring. The formal
definition is exactly as above, but we relax the requirement that R be a field, and instead
allow an arbitrary ring. We have written the product rx with the scalar r on the left, and
technically we get a left R-module over the ring R. The axioms of a right R-module are
(x + y)r = xr + yr; x(r + s) = xr + xs; (xs)r = x(sr), x1 = x.
“Module” will always mean left module unless stated otherwise. Most of the time, there
is no reason to switch the scalars from one side to the other (especially if the underlying
ring is commutative). But there are cases where we must be very careful to distinguish
between left and right modules (see Example 6 of (4.1.3)).
4.1.2 Some Basic Properties ofModules
Let M be an R-module. The techni
2 CHAPTER 4. MODULE FUNDAMENTALS
(3) (−r)x = r(−x) = −(rx) [as in (2) of (2.1.1) with a replaced by r and b by x]
(4) If R is a field, or more generally a division ring, then rx = 0M implies that either
r = 0R or x = 0M. [If r = 0, multiply the equation rx = 0M by r−1.]
4.1.3 Examples
1. If M is a vector space over the field R, then M is an R-module.
2. Any ring R is a module over itself. Rather than check all the formal requirements,
think intuitively: Elements of a ring can be added and subtracted, and we can
certainly multiply r ∈ R by x ∈ R, and the usual rules of arithmetic apply.
3. If R is any ring, then Rn, the set of all n-tuples with components in R, is an
R-module, with the usual definitions of addition and scalar multiplication (as in
Euclidean space, e.g., r(x1,...,xn)=(rx1,...,rxn), etc).
4. Let M = Mmn(R) be the set of all m × n matrices with entries in R. Then M is
an R-module, where addition is ordinary matrix addition, and multiplication of the
scalar c by the matrix A means multiplication of each entry of A by c.
5. Every abelian group A is a Z-module. Addition and subtraction is carried out
according to the group structure of A; the key point is that we can multiply x ∈ A
by the integer n. If n > 0, then nx = x + x + ··· + x (n times); if n < 0, then
nx = −x − x −···− x (|n| times).
In all of these examples, we can switch from left to right modules by a simple notational
change. This is definitely not the case in the next example.
6. Let I be a left ideal of the ring R; then I is a left R-module. (If x ∈ I and r ∈ R
then rx (but not necessarily xr) belongs to I.) Similarly, a right ideal is a right
R-module, and a two-sided ideal is both a left and a right R-module.
An R-module M permits addition of vectors and scalar multiplication. If multiplication of vectors is allowed, we have an R-algebra.
4.1.4 Definitions and Comments
Let R be a commutative ring. We say that M is an algebra over R, or that M is an
R-algebra, if M is an R-module that is also a ring (not necessarily commutative), and the
ring and module operations are compatible, i.e.,
r(xy)=(rx)y = x(ry) for all x, y ∈ M and r ∈ R.
4.1.5 Examples
1. Every commutative ring R is an algebra over itself (see Example 2 of (4.1.3)).
2. An arbitrary ring R is always a Z-algebra (see Example 5 of (4.1.3)).
4.1. MODULES AND ALGEBRAS 3
3. If R is a commutative ring, then Mn(R), the set of all n × n matrices with entries
in R, is an R-algebra (see Example 4 of (4.1.3)).
4. If R is a commutative ring, then the polynomial ring R[X] is an R-algebra, as
is the ring R[[X]] of formal power series; see Examples 5 and 6 of (2.1.3). The
compatibility condition is satisfied because an element of R can be regarded as a
polynomial of degree 0.
5. If E/F is a field extension, then E is an algebra over F. This continues to hold if E
is a division ring, and in this case we say that E is a division algebra over F.
To check that a subset S of a vector space is a subspace, we verify that S is closed
under addition of vectors and multiplication of a vector by a scalar. Exactly the same
idea applies to modules and algebras.
4.1.6 Definitions and Comments
If N is a nonempty subset of the R-module M, we say that N is a submodule of M
(notation N ≤ M) if for every x, y ∈ N and r, s ∈ R, we have rx + sy ∈ N. If M is an
R-algebra, we say that N is a subalgebra if N is a submodule that is also a subring.
For example, if A is an abelian group (= Z-module), the submodules of A are the
subsets closed under addition and multiplication by an integer (which amounts to addition
also). Thus the submodules of A are simply the subgroups. If R is a ring, hence a
module over itself, the submodules are those subsets closed under addition and also under
multiplication by any r ∈ R, in other words, the left ideals. (If we take R to be a right
R-module, then the submodules are the right ideals.)
We can produce many examples of subspaces of vector spaces by considering kernels
and images of linear transformations. A similar idea applies to modules.
4.1.7 Definitions and Comments
Let M and N be R-modules. A module homomorphism (also called an R-homomorphism)
from M to N is a map f : M → N such that
f(rx + sy) = rf(x) + sf(y) for all x, y ∈ M and r, s ∈ R.
Equivalently, f(x + y) = f(x) + f(y) and f(rx) = rf(x) for all x, y ∈ M and r ∈ R.
The kernel of a homomorphism f is ker f = {x ∈ M : f(x)=0}, and the image of f
is {f(x): x ∈ M}.
If follows from the definitions that the kernel of f is a submodule of M, and the image
of f is a submodule of N.
If M and N are R-algebras, an algebra homomorphism or homomorphism of algebras
from M to N is an R-module homomorphism that is also a ring homomorphism.
4.1.8 Another Way to Describe an Algebra
Assume that A is an algebra over the commutative ring R, and consider the map r → r1
of R into A. The commutativity of R and the compatibility of the ring and module
4 CHAPTER 4. MODULE FUNDAMENTALS
operations imply that the map is a ring homomorphism. To see this, note that if r, s ∈ R
then
(rs)1 = (sr)1 = s(r1) = s[(r1)1] = (r1)(s1).
Furthermore, if y ∈ A then
(r1)y = r(1y) = r(y1) = y(r1)
so that r1 belongs to the center of A, i.e., the set of elements that commute with everything
in A.
Conversely, if f is a ring homomorphism from the commutative ring R to the center
of the ring A, we can make A into an R-module via rx = f(r)x. The compatibility
conditions are satisfied because
r(xy) = f(r)(xy)=(f(r)x)y = (rx)y
and
(f(r)x)y = (xf(r))y = x(f(r)y) = x(ry).
Because of this result, the definition of an R-algebra is sometimes given as follows. The
ring A is an algebra over the commutative ring R if there exists a ring homomorphism of
R into the center of A. For us at this stage, such a definition would be a severe overdose
of abstraction.
Notational Convention: We will often write the module {0} (and the ideal {0} in
a ring) simply as 0.
Problems For Section 4.1
1. If I is an ideal of the ring R, show how to make the quotient ring R/I into a left
R-module, and also show how to make R/I into a right R-module.
2. Let A be a commutative ring and F a field. Show that A is an algebra over F if and
only if A contains (an isomorphic copy of) F as a subring.
Problems 3, 4 and 5 illustrate that familiar properties of vector spaces need not hold
for modules.
3. Give an example of an R-module M with nonzero elements r ∈ R and x ∈ M such
that rx = 0.
4. Let M be the additive group of rational numbers. Show that any two elements of M
are linearly dependent (over the integers Z).
5. Continuing Problem 4, show that M cannot have a basis, that is, a linearly independent
spanning set over Z.
6. Prove the modular law for subgroups of a given group G: With the group operation
written multiplicatively,
A(B ∩ C)=(AB) ∩ C
4.2. THE ISOMORPHISM THEOREMS FOR MODULES 5
if A ⊆ C. Switching to additive notation, we have, for submodules of a given R-module,
A + (B ∩ C)=(A + B) ∩ C,
again if A ⊆ C.
7. Let T be a linear transformation on the vector space V over the field F. Show how to
make V into an R-module in a natural way, where R is the polynomial ring F[X].
4.2 The Isomorphism Theorems For Modules
If N is a submodule of the R-module M (notation N ≤ M), then in particular N is an
additive subgroup of M, and we may form the quotient group M/N in the usual way.
In fact M/N becomes an R-module if we define r(x + N) = rx + N. (This makes sense
because if x belongs to the submodule N, so does rx.) Since scalar multiplication in the
quotient module M/N is carried out via scalar multiplication in the original module M,
we can check the module axioms without difficulty. The canonical map π : M → M/N is
a module homomorphism with kernel N. Just as with groups and rings, we can establish
the basic isomorphism theorems for modules.
4.2.1 Factor Theorem For Modules
Any module homomorphism f : M → M whose kernel contains N can be factored through
M/N. In other words, there is a unique module homomorphism f : M/N → M such that
f(x+N) = f(x). Furthermore, (i) f is an epimorphism if and only if f is an epimorphism;
(ii) f is a monomorphism if and only if ker f = N; (iii) f is an isomorphism if and only
if f is a epimorphism and kerf = N.
Proof. Exactly as in (2.3.1), with appropriate notational changes. (In Figure 2.3.1, replace
R by M, S by M and I by N.)
4.2.2 First Isomorphism Theorem For Modules
If f : M → M is a module homomorphism with kernel N, then the image of f is isomorphic to M/N.
Proof. Apply the factor theorem, and note that f is an epimorphism onto its image.
4.2.3 Second Isomorphism Theorem For Modules
Let S and T be submodules of M, and let S + T = {x + y : x ∈ S,y ∈ T}. Then S + T
and S ∩ T are submodules of M and
(S + T)/T ∼= S/(S ∩ T).
Proof. The module axioms for S + T and S ∩T can be checked in routine fashion. Define
a map f : S → M/T by f(x) = x + T. Then f is a module homomorphism whose kernel
is S ∩T and whose image is {x+T : x ∈ S} = (S +T)/T. The first isomorphism theorem
for modules gives the desired result. ♣
6 CHAPTER 4. MODULE FUNDAMENTALS
4.2.4 Third Isomorphism Theorem For Modules
If N ≤ L ≤ M, then
M/L ∼= (M/N)/(L/N).
Proof. Define f : M/N → M/L by f(x + N) = x + L. As in (2.3.4), the kernel of f is
{x+N : x ∈ L} = L/N, and the image of f is {x+L: x ∈ M} = M/L. The result follows
from the first isomorphism theorem for modules.
4.2.5 Correspondence Theorem For Modules
Let N be a submodule of the R-module M. The map S → S/N sets up a one-to-one
correspondence between the set of all submodules of M containing N and the set of all
submodules of M/N. The inverse of the map is T → π−1(T), where π is the canonical
map: M → M/N.
Proof. The correspondence theorem for groups yields a one-to-one correspondence between additive subgroups of M containing N and additive subgroups of M/N. We
must check that submodules correspond to submodules, and it is sufficient to show
that if S1/N ≤ S2/N, then S1 ≤ S2 (the converse is immediate). If x ∈ S1, then
x + N ∈ S1/N ⊆ S2/N, so x + N = y + N for some y ∈ S2. Thus x − y ∈ N ⊆ S2, and
since y ∈ S2 we must have x ∈ S2 as well. The ore S1 ≤ S2.
We now look at modules that have a particularly simple structure, and can be used
as building blocks for more complicated modules.
4.2.6 Definitions and Comments
An R-module M is cyclic if it is generated by a single element x. In other words,
M = Rx = {rx: r ∈ R}.
Thus every element of M is a scalar multiple of x. (If x = 0, then M = {0}, which is
called the zero module and is often written simply as 0.) A cyclic vector space over a field
is a one-dimensional space, assuming that x = 0.
The annihilator of an element y in the R-module M is Iy = {r ∈ R: ry = 0}, a left
ideal of R. If R is commutative, and M is cyclic with generator x, then M ∼= R/Ix.
To see this, apply the first isomorphism theorem for modules to the map r → rx of R
onto M. The annihilator of the module M is Io = {r ∈ R: ry = 0 for every y ∈ M}.
Note that Io is a two-sided ideal, because if r ∈ I0 and s ∈ R, then for every y ∈ M we
have (rs)y = r(sy) = 0. When R is commutative, annihilating the generator of a cyclic
module is equivalent to annihilating the entire module.
4.3. DIRECT SUMS AND FREE MODULES 7
4.2.7 Lemma
(a) If x generates a cyclic module M over the commutative ring R, then Ix = Io, so
that M ∼= R/Io. (In this situation, Io is frequently referred to as the order ideal of M.)
(b) Two cyclic R-modules over a commutative ring are isomorphic if and only if they
have the same annihilator.
Proof. (a) If rx = 0 and y ∈ M, then y = sx for some s ∈ R, so ry = r(sx) = s(rx) =
s0 = 0. Conversely, if r annihilates M, then in particular, rx = 0.
(b) The “if” part follows from (a), so assume that g : Rx → Ry is an isomorphism
of cyclic R-modules. Since g is an isomorphism, g(x) must be a generator of Ry, so we
may as well take g(x) = y. Then g(rx) = rg(x) = ry, so rx corresponds to ry under the
isomorphism. Therefore r belongs to the annihilator of Rx if and only if r belongs to the
annihilator of Ry.
Problems For Section 4.2
1. Show that every submodule of the quotient module M/N can be expressed as (L+N)/N
for some submodule L of M.
2. In Problem 1, must L contain N?
3. In the matrix ring Mn(R), let M be the submodule generated by E11, the matrix with
1 in row 1, column 1, and 0’s elsewhere. Thus M = {AE11 : A ∈ Mn(R)}. Show that
M consists of all matrices whose entries are zero except perhaps in column 1.
4. Continuing Problem 3, show that the annihilator of E11 consists of all matrices whose
first column is zero, but the annihilator of M is {0}.
5. If I is an ideal of the ring R, show that R/I is a cyclic R-module.
6. Let M be an R-module, and let I be an ideal of R. We wish to make M into an
R/I-module via (r + I)m = rm, r ∈ R,m ∈ M. When will this be legal?
7. Assuming legality in Problem 6, let M1 be the resulting R/I-module, and note that as
sets, M1 = M. Let N be a subset of M and consider the following two statements:
(a) N is an R-submodule of M;
(b) N is an R/I-submodule of M1.
Can one of these statements be true and the other false?
4.3 Direct Sums and Free Modules
4.3.1 Direct Products
In Section 1.5, we studied direct products of groups, and the basic idea seems to carry
over to modules. Suppose that we have an R-module Mi for each i in some index set I
(possibly infinite). The members of the direct product of the Mi, denoted by
i∈I Mi, are
all families (ai, i ∈ I), where ai ∈ Mi. (A family is just a function on I whose value at the
element i is ai.) Addition is described by (ai)+(bi)=(ai + bi) and scalar multiplication
by r(ai)=(rai).
8 CHAPTER 4. MODULE FUNDAMENTALS
There is nothing wrong with this definition, but the resulting mathematical object has
some properties that are undesirable. If (ei) is the family with 1 in position i and zeros
elsewhere, then (thinking about vector spaces) it would be useful to express an arbitrary
element of the direct product in terms of the ei. But if the index set I is infinite, we
will need concepts of limit and convergence, and this will take us out of algebra and into
analysis. Another approach is to modify the definition of direct product.
4.3.2 Definitions
The external direct sum of the modules Mi, i ∈ I, denoted by ⊕i∈IMi, consists of all
families (ai, i ∈ I) with ai ∈ Mi, such that ai = 0 for all but finitely many i. Addition
and scalar multiplication are defined exactly as for the direct product, so that the external
direct sum coincides with the direct product when the index set I is finite.
The R-module M is the internal direct sum of the submodules Mi if each x ∈ M can
be expressed uniquely as xi1 + ··· + xin where 0 = xik ∈ Mik , k = 1,...,n. (The positive
integer n and the elements xik depend on x. In any expression of this type, the indices
ik are assumed distinct.)
Just as with groups, the internal and external direct sums are isomorphic. To see this
without a lot of formalism, let the element xik ∈ Mik correspond to the family that has
xik in position ik and zeros elsewhere. We will follow standard practice and refer to the
“direct sum” without the qualifying adjective. Again as with groups, the next result may
help us to recognize when a module can be expressed as a direct sum.
4.3.3 Proposition
The module M is the direct sum of submodules Mi if and only if both of the following
conditions are satisfied:
(1) M =
i Mi, that is, each x ∈ M is a finite sum of the form xi1 + ··· + xin , where
xik ∈ Mik ;
(2) For each i, Mi ∩
j=i Mj = 0.
(Note that in condition (1), we do not assume that the representation is unique. Observe
also that another way of expressing (2) is that if xi1 + ··· + xin = 0, with xik ∈ Mik , then
xik = 0 for all k.)
Proof. The necessity of the conditions follows from the definition of external direct sum,
so assume that (1) and (2) hold. If x ∈ M then by (1), x is a finite sum of elements
from various Mi’s. For convenience in notation, say x = x1 + x2 + x3 + x4 with xi ∈ Mi,
i = 1, 2, 3, 4. If the representation is not unique, say x = y1 + y2 + y4 + y5 + y6 with
yi ∈ Mi, i = 1, 2, 4, 5, 6. Then x3 is a sum of terms from modules other than M3, so
by (2), x3 = 0. Similarly, y5 = y6 = 0 and we have x1 + x2 + x4 = y1 + y2 + y4. But
then x1 − y1 is a sum of terms from modules other than M1, so by (2), x1 = y1. Similarly
x2 = y2, x4 = y4, and the result follows.
4.3. DIRECT SUMS AND FREE MODULES 9
A basic property of the direct sum M = ⊕i∈IMi is that homomorphisms fi : Mi → N
can be “lifted” to M. In other words, there is a unique homomorphism f : M → N such
that for each i, f = fi on Mi. Explicitly,
f(xi1 + ··· + xir ) = fi1 (xi1 ) + ··· + fir (xir ).
[No other choice is possible for f, and since each fi is a homomorphism, so is f.]
We know that every vector space has a basis, but not every module is so fortunate;
see Section 4.1, Problem 5. We now examine modules that have this feature.