Recently, Khachian [3] presented a short algorithm for determining the
consistency, i.e., solvability, of a finite set of linear inequalities in R” (cf.
also [5]). More precisely, if
a,,x, + . . . +%A < b,
a,,,,~, + . . , +amnx,, < b,,,
x, >o,...,x, >o
(*)
is a system of inequalities in R” for which the ati’s and hi’s are integers, the
algorithm will determine whether or not (*) has a solution, and locate a
solution if there is one. Furthermore, it does this in such a way that the
required accuracy, memory requirements, and running time are bounded
by fixed polynomials in n and L, where L is the complexity of the system
as measured by the number of bits needed to encode (a).
Remarks. 1. The requirement that the solution set lie in the positive
orthant is a standard one in linear programming, and a problem without
this constraint can very easily be replaced by an equivalent one satisfying
this requirement (cf. [l, p. 861).
2. As is shown in [2], the consistency of an integer system in which
the inequalities are weak, i.e., of the form “ I ” can be made equivalent to
that of a system of strict integer inequalities. Moreover, a system of weak
integer inequalities can in practice be approximated by a system of
rational, and hence integer strict, inequalities. Finally, if a problem involves an auxiliary linear form which is to be maximized subject to a
system of weak inequalities, it can be changed into a system without a
maximization constraint by adjoining the dual problem, together with the
requirement that the forms to be extremalized in the respective problems
be equal (cf. [l, p. 1291).
The papers of Khachian and Shor are in the style of brief research
announcements and do not contain proofs of several assertions required to
1
019fS8858/80/01000-06$05.00/O
Copyright 0 1980 by Academic press, Inc.
All rights of reproduction in any form reserved. 
2 BURTON RANDOL
establish the algorithm. Some proofs have recently been provided in [2].
All of these papers focus mainly on algebraic descriptions of the algorithm,
and in the case of [3], on the necessary detailed accuracy, memory, and
running time estimates. It is the purpose of this paper to sketch briefly the
extremely simple geometric idea involved in the algorithm, and then
describe a possible improvement suggested by A. T. Vasquez.
Basically, the technique is very evocative of one of the standard approaches to the Heine-Bore1 theorem-repetitive bisection. The new idea
is that since the bisecting hyperplanes which arise can be tilted in random
ways, it is extremely advantageous to make the repeated bisections involve
a figure which is invariant under affine transformations, e.g., a halfellipsoid. In particular, because of this affine invariance, a certain circumscribing lemma has the same geometric form at all stages of the process.
In more detail, after setting A, = jaUj + 1, Bi = jbil + 1, and M = (the
product of all the Ati’s and Bi’s), one begins with the following simple
observations:
A. If (*) is consistent, then the coordinate entries of any vertex are
rational numbers whose numerators and denominators are less than M.
Thus, if (*) is consistent, it always has a solution within the open ball B, of
radius fi M about the origin.
B. If (*) is consistent, the volume of the portion of the solution set
which lies in B, is greater than I’, = (,!)-‘M-(n+‘). (As is remarked in [2],
the quantity V, is itself of the form 2-‘(“, L), where P(n, L) is a linear
polynomial in n and L.)
A and B are proved in [2], and are also familiar from the geometry of
numbers. To prove A, one observes that any coordinate entry of a vertex
of the solution polyhedron must be a solution of an n by n integer linear
system with entries of the form 0, 1, aii, and bi, and hence, is expressible as
the quotient of two determinants with such entries. Each determinant can
be trivially bounded by replacing it by the product of the sums of the
absolute values of the rows, which in turn is dominated by M, which
proves A. To prove B, one observes that the solution polyhedron must
have at least one vertex, since it is contained in the positive orthant. Such a
vertex must, of course, lie in B,. The solution polyhedron may or may not
have n + 1 vertices in general position, but if it does not, the problem can
be augmented by the additional constraints x, < M, . . . , x, < M without
disrupting the presence of a vertex, and hence, a solution within B,. These
additional constraints cause the solution polyhedron to have compact
closure, and hence, certainly produce n + 1 vertices in general position in
x0. The volume of the simplex spanned by these vertices is 
ELLIPSOID METHOD IN LINEAR PROGRAMMING 3
FIGURE 1
where u,, . . . , u,, , are column vectors representing the vertices. Since the
determinant is a rational number whose numerator is not zero, and since
the denominators of the entries of any fixed vertex are all the same and
less than M, the result follows immediately, if we combine the formal
expansion of the determinant into a single fraction.
The next observation is of a purely geometric character. If E, is an open
ellipsoid in R”, and ET denotes the intersection of E, with a closed
half-space not containing more than half of E, and having boundary
hyperplane H, then there exists a second open ellipsoid E2, such that E,
contains E:, and (vo~( E,))/(vol(E,)) < e - ‘iZn. Since the truth of this
assertion is an affine invariant, it suffices to establish it in the case in
which E, is the unit ball centered at the origin, and H is given by xn = d,
with 0 I d < 1 (Fig. 1).
If we require the circumscribing ellipsoid to be rotationally invariant
about the x,, axis, it follows quickly from the calculus that the center of the
minimal circumscribing ellipsoid is located at distance (nd + l)/(n + 1)
from the origin, and its short semi-axis is (n/ (n + l))(l - d), while the
long semi-axes are identical, and of length (n’/ (rz’ - 1))‘12( 1 - d2)‘j2. It
follows that the ratio of the volume to that of the unit ball in the worst
possible case when d = 0 is (n/ (n + l))(n”/ (n’ - l))(“-I)” = r,,. This
quantity is less than 1 if and only if its logarithm is less than zero. After a
little manipulation, the statement about logarithms becomes log(1 + n-i)
+ #I - 1) log(1 - rr-‘) > 0, which follows from the power series expansions for log(1 + x) and log(1 - x2). Although r,, + 1 as n -+ cc, it follows
immediately from the power series expansions that r,, is always less than
e-‘i2”. Finally, if E, is specified by giving both its center p,, and the
symmetric matrix E; of the quadratic form inverse to the form defining the
ellipsoid obtained by parallel translating E, to the origin, and if one is
given the hyperplane H, then the determination of the center of E2 and the
matrix E; is not very time-consuming. Indeed, suppose that T, is a linear
transformation which takes the unit ball into E,. (To save notation, we 
4 BURTON RANDOL
assume that T, is symmetric.) Now the hyperplane H will in practice be
given by one of the inequalities in (*). If a = (ail, . . . , a,,) is the vector
corresponding to this inequality, it is a simple exercise in affine geometry
to show that the image under T, of the point of tangency of the circumscribing ellipsoid in the ball model is s]I T,a]] - ‘Tfu, where
S = Si!Zn(bi - (GPJ), and hence, the center of E, is obtained by displacing the center of E, by s(nd + l)(n + 1))‘~(T,u~l-‘T&z = s(nd + l)(n +
l)-‘(Ei’u, u)-‘/~E;u. (The algorithm as stated in [2] has the wrong sign for
the displacement vector.)
To find E; we proceed as follows. Suppose B is a unit vector. Denote by
E,*(d) the ellipsoid obtained by translating the circumscribing ellipsoid of
Fig. 1 to the origin and then subjecting it to an orthogonal transformation
which takes the north pole into 9. It is then evident that E,*(d) is the image
of the unit ball under a transformation of the form c,Z + c2PB, where
PO is the projection along 8, cl =(n2/ (n’ - 1))li2(1 - d2)‘i2, and
c2 =(n/ (n + l))(l - d) - cl. A transformation taking the unit ball into
E2 will then be given by T2 = T,(c,Z + c,P,), which is generally not
symmetric. (Note that the matrix PO is simply (O,$) = 80’, if 8 is written as
a column vector with entries O,, . . . , O,.)
NOW Ei = T2Ti = T,(c,Z + c~P~)~T, = cfTf + (2c,c, + c$TIPBT1. In
the case at hand, 8 = s]I T,~ll-~T,u. It follows that
p* = II ~141-2(~14(~14 = 11~1~11-2(~,)(~)(~)‘(~,),
so
T,PoT, = II ~,~ll-2(~:)(~)(~)‘(T,)2
= IlT,uIl-“(T;u)(2’$z)~ = (E;u, a)-‘(E;a)(E;u)‘;
i.e.,
Ei = c,E; + (2~1~2 + Ci)(E;Uy a)-‘(E;a)(E;a)‘*
It remains to calculate d. But it is evident from affine geometry that d
can be very simply calculated as follows: Let D be the distance from the
origin to the point of intersection of the hyperplane H with the line
determined by a. Let D’ = )I T,all-‘IIT$l( = (E;u, u)-‘/~~IE~u~(. Then
d = D/Or.
We now describe the algorithm and then the proposed modification. The
algorithm is this. Define a sequence E,, E2, . . . of ellipsoids as follows:
Set E, = B,. As has been remarked, if (*) is consistent, then E, must
contain a piece S of the solution set having volume at least V,,. Assuming
for the moment that (*) is consistent, we take as our first trial solution the 
ELLIPSOID METHOD IN LINEAR PROGRAMMING 5
FIGURE 2
origin. If the origin satisfies (q) we are done. If not, there exists an
inequality in (*) which is violated at the origin. Take the hyperplane H
corresponding to this inequality, and parallel translate it to the center of
E,. Call the result H’. (See Fig. 2.)
Let i E, be the intersection of E, with the half-space determined by H’
which contains S. By a previous argument, there exists an ellipsoid E2
containing i E,, and such that vol( E2) 5 r,, vol(E,) (note that E, contains
S). Take the center of E, as the next trial solution. If it satisfies (*) stop. If
not, there is an inequality in (*) which is violated at the center of E,. If this
is the case, repeat the just-described process. In this way, one constructs a
sequence E,, E,, . . . of ellipsoids, each one of which contains S, and the
volumes of which are decreasing exponentially. Ultimately this will come
into conflict with the fact that S has volume greater than V,, so a solution
must be obtained before this happens. The number of repetitions of the
process required to achieve this for a fixed n will be O(log R), where
R = (vol(B,))/ I’,, and this estimate is polynomial in n and L. Since rn + 1
as n + 00, the adjusting constant implicit in the estimate will tend to
infinity as n + 00. On the other hand, since r,” < e-i/*, it is evident that
there exists a constant C, such that at the very worst the number of
repetitions is bounded by Cn log R, which is also a polynomial estimate in 
6 BURTON RANDOL
n and L. Finally, note that if (*) is not consistent, this will be detected by
the algorithm, since if it has not obtained a solution after the above
number of repetitions, then there cannot be a solution.
We conclude with the modification, which at this point can be stated
very quickly. It seems quite clear that it may be very inefficient to
repeatedly translate H back to H’, and so always deal with half-ellipsoids.
As we have seen, very little additional computational complexity is introduced by circumscribing instead the intersection of Ej with the “good”
side of H. Computationally, the modified algorithm is the same as the
original algorithm, with the change that c, and c2 now involve d, and
hence, are changing at each step. Additionally, it should be worthwhile to
search for a distant H at each stage. Clearly, the estimated running time of
the modified algorithm will depend on the accumulated products of the
ratios (vol Ei+,)/(vol Ei), but can in no case be longer than the estimated
running time of the original algorithm. Finally, we remark that recently
several additional modifications of an empirical character have been
proposed to accelerate the procedure, and as experience accumulates, some
of these may be incorporated into various working versions of the algorithm (cf., e.g., [4, 6, and 71). 